Finding Aid for Robert E. Lewis papers, 1972-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Miscellaneous Professional Files
  The third file contains the final installment of the printed MED, Middle English Dictionary: Plan and Bibliography, 2nd edition (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 2007), which contains a thoroughly revised and expanded Plan (now called "History, Contents, and Guide to the Dictionary") written by Lewis; and a revised Bibliography, combining the original bibliography (1954), the supplement to it (1984), and the books and articles added made between 1984 and 2001, complied by Lewis and Mary Jane Williams, with assistance from Marilyn S. Miller. Three reviews have been added at the end of the file.
  Unpublished Papers on Medieval Topics contains, first, a list of papers presented by Lewis on various public occasions and, second, a selection of six of these and others. The first two papers are on the list and are checked. (The papers on the Prick(e) of Conscience (1974-76) are either in Boxes 1 and 2 and/or were incorporated into publications in Box 3 or in the subseries Publications above; the papers on "Word/Linguistic Geography" from 1992-93 are in Box 2; the papers on the MED were incorporated into publications on that subject either in the subseries Publications or in the subseries Books and Reviews above.) The next three papers, unlisted ("Old and Middle English Language and Literature," "Some Brief Remarks on the Fourteenth Century in England," and "Textual Criticism: M[iddle] E[nglish] Texts"), were presented as guest lectures in graduate courses at Indiana University. The final paper, also unlisted, is a brief appreciation of a former editor at the MED, Lister Matheson, presented at his memorial service at Michigan State University in 2012.
  Correspondence with Influential Scholars contains files on four scholars who were influential in Lewis's professional career. The influential scholars include: Howard C. Rice, Jr, Robert A. Pratt, Neil R. Ker, and Angus McIntosh. Each of the folders contains a statement written by Lewis on the importance of each scholar to his work. The files typically include correspondence with the scholars, cards, miscellany, obituaries, and correspondence with other colleagues and in some cases the surviving spouses.
  Fellowships and Research Grants contains, first, a list of the fellowships and grants received by Lewis during his career and, second, details of a selection of these awards (as Lewis's remaining records warrant), in chronological order.
  Awards consists of three files. These contain details of awards received by Lewis in the year and a half following the completion of the MED: (1) a Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award from the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor, on 2 October 2002 (award letter first, with the other items following, chronologically arranged within the award folder); (2) election as a Fellow of the Dictionary Society of North America at its biennial meeting in Durham, NC, in May of 2003 (the DSNA Newsletter account of the meeting first, with the other two items following, chronologically arranged within the Newsletter); and (3) the Sir Israel Gollancz Memorial Prize for English Studies from the British Academy in London, on 13 October 2003 (award letter first, with the other items following, chronologically arranged).
  Appointment and Retirement, contains two files. The first is divided into: (1) letters and memos regarding Lewis's appointment at the University of Michigan in the fall of 1981; (2) his annual reports to the Department of English from his first full year, 1982-83, through his last, 2002-2003; and (3) an up-to-date (2012) copy of his Curriculum Vitae. The second file is about Lewis's retirement on 31 December 2003 (retirement memoir first, with the other two items following, chronologically arranged within the retirement-memoir folder).
  - Celebration of Completion of the Middle English Dictionary (Box 5)
  - Materials from the Dictionary Society of North America meeting, exhibits, celebratory dinner, etc. May 2001
    - Articles about the completion of the MED, 2001-2002 (Box 5)
    - Congratulatory letters and cards, chiefly personal 2001-2002 (Box 5)
    - Photographs taken during the celebrations May 2001 (Box 5)
    - Special issue of the journal Dictionaries, 2002 (Box 5)
  - Middle English Dictionary Miscellaneous
    - Articles on the MED, 1982-1995, 2005 (Box 5)
    - Various MED"memory" items (Box 5)
    - Photographs
      - MED offices, 555 South Forest, Ann Arbor, 1980s-2001 (Box 5)
      - MED staff and events off-site, 1982-2001 (Box 5)
      - Visiting Japanese scholars 1991-2002 (Box 5)
    - CD of "Alphabet Odyssey," a program on the MED on the Canadian Broadcasting Company radio program "Ideas," 2004, 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 5)
  - Publications (Articles, Notes, etc.)
    - 1961-2012, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Books and Reviews
    - Lotario dei Segni (Pope Innocent III) De Miseria Condicionis Humane and related items (primarily reviews), 1978 (Box 5)
    - Index of Printed Middle English Prose and possible supplement, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Middle English Dictionary: Plan and Bibliography, 2nd edition with reviews, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Unpublished Papers on Medieval Topics 1974-2012 (Box 5)
  - Influential Scholars
    - Howard C. Rice, Jr. 1962-1980 (Box 5)
    - Robert A. Pratt 1963-1987 and subsequent (Box 5)
    - Neil R. Ker 1968-1982 and subsequent (Box 5)
    - Angus McIntosh 1972-2005 and subsequent (Box 5)
  - Fellowships and Research Grants 1964-1993 (Box 5)
  - Awards 2002-2003 (Box 5)
  - Appointment and Retirement 1981-2003
Material relating to Robert E. Lewis as editor of the Middle English Dictionary can be found in the record group Middle English Dictionary records also housed at the Bentley Historical Library.